package prometheus // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/extensions/prometheus"


TYPES

type Collector struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    Collector is a prometheus.Collector integration for the scheduler.

    Behavior: It bridges CRS metrics into the Prometheus ecosystem safely.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. Prometheus scrape calls operate
    concurrently against the provider's Snapshot.

func NewCollector(provider MetricsProvider, telemetry TelemetryProvider) *Collector
    NewCollector constructs a Prometheus Collector.

    Behavior: The telemetry provider is optional. If nil, throughput metrics
    (adds, acquires) will not be exported.

    Lifecycle: The returned Collector must be registered with a
    prometheus.Registry.

func (c *Collector) Collect(ch chan<- prometheus.Metric)
    Collect executes the metric gathering and writes to the Prometheus channel.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It performs a rapid O(H) stats snapshot
    and an O(1) atomic telemetry read.

func (c *Collector) Describe(ch chan<- *prometheus.Desc)
    Describe sends all possible metric descriptions to the Prometheus channel.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe as per the prometheus.Collector
    contract.

type MetricsProvider interface {
	Stats() stats.Stats
}
    MetricsProvider defines the interface for retrieving core scheduler stats.

    Behavior: Allows the Collector to snapshot O(H) structural metrics like heap
    counts.

type TelemetryProvider interface {
	Snapshot() metrics.TelemetryStats
}
    TelemetryProvider defines the interface for retrieving O(1) throughput
    metrics.

    Behavior: Allows the Collector to retrieve lock-free event counters from the
    TelemetryObserver.

