package config // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/config"


CONSTANTS

const (
	// DefaultHeapCount is the default number of Heap Shards when none is specified.
	DefaultHeapCount = 1
)

TYPES

type AcquirePolicy uint8
    AcquirePolicy determines whether an acquired resource remains active or
    becomes exclusively locked.

    Behavior: Shared leaves the resource active for concurrent acquires.
    Exclusive moves the resource to the Inactive Store until explicitly
    released.

const (
	// Shared returns a resource while leaving it ACTIVE in its Heap Shard.
	Shared AcquirePolicy = iota
	// Exclusive removes a resource from its Heap Shard, places it INACTIVE in the
	// Inactive Store, and requires Release before it can be acquired again.
	Exclusive
)
type Comparator[T any] func(a, b T) int
    Comparator defines resource priority. A negative result ranks a ahead of b;
    zero gives no tie-order guarantee; a positive result ranks b ahead.

    Behavior & Ownership: The caller completely owns the logic. The scheduler
    uses this function to organize resources internally.

    Concurrency Guarantees: It MUST be deterministic, thread-safe, and
    non-blocking. It is invoked while the scheduler holds internal shard locks,
    so it MUST NEVER call back into the scheduler.

type Config[T any, ID comparable] struct {
	// HeapCount is the number of Heap Shards. 1 means one global priority heap.
	HeapCount int
	// Comparator is the non-nil priority ordering function.
	Comparator Comparator[T]
	// KeyFunc is the non-nil application-key extractor.
	KeyFunc KeyFunc[T, ID]
	// AcquirePolicy is Shared or Exclusive; immutable after construction.
	AcquirePolicy AcquirePolicy
	// AcquireStrategy is the optional acquire-shard selection policy.
	AcquireStrategy acquire.AcquireStrategy
	// Observers receives read-only lifecycle events.
	Observers []events.Observer[ID]
}
    Config provides the complete configuration required to instantiate a
    Scheduler.

    Lifecycle: A Config is strictly validated during scheduler.New(). After
    the scheduler is created, the configuration becomes immutable and cannot be
    modified.

func Validate[T any, ID comparable](cfg Config[T, ID]) (Config[T, ID], error)
    Validate applies default values and enforces Phase 1 validation rules on the
    Config.

    Behavior: It checks for a valid HeapCount, non-nil Comparator, non-nil
    KeyFunc, and a recognized AcquirePolicy.

    Complexity: O(1).

type KeyFunc[T any, ID comparable] func(resource T) ID
    KeyFunc extracts a unique identity from a generic resource.

    Behavior & Ownership: The caller completely owns resource identity.
    The scheduler uses this identity to manage the resource's lifecycle across
    active and inactive states.

    Concurrency Guarantees: It must be deterministic and pure. It is invoked
    frequently during O(1) lookups and MUST NOT block.

