package scheduler // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/scheduler"


TYPES

type Scheduler[T any, ID comparable] struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    Scheduler is a highly concurrent, lock-sharded priority queue for generic
    resources. It orchestrates resource acquisition across multiple internal
    Heap Shards using a configurable AcquireStrategy. It enforces thread-safe
    mutations, atomic state transitions between ACTIVE and INACTIVE states,
    and non-blocking telemetry dispatch.

    Concurrency Guarantees: All exported methods are completely thread-safe.
    The scheduler avoids global mutexes in favor of fine-grained per-shard
    locking and O(1) concurrent-safe maps.

    Lifecycle: A Scheduler is created via New() and must eventually be stopped
    via Shutdown() to release background goroutines.

func New[T any, ID comparable](cfg config.Config[T, ID]) (*Scheduler[T, ID], error)
    New creates, validates, and initializes a new Scheduler instance. It applies
    default configuration values, validates the constraints (such as positive
    heap counts and non-nil KeyFunc), allocates the internal shard array,
    and starts the background event dispatcher goroutine.

    Complexity: O(H) where H is the number of Heap Shards.

    Lifecycle: The returned Scheduler must be terminated with Shutdown() to
    prevent goroutine leaks.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Acquire() (T, error)
    Acquire retrieves the highest priority resource from the scheduler.
    It delegates to the configured AcquireStrategy to select a candidate Heap
    Shard, checking shards sequentially until an available resource is found.
    If the policy is Exclusive, the resource is atomically moved to the Inactive
    Store.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It only locks one Heap Shard at a time,
    distributing contention across shards. scalability without global lock
    contention.

    Complexity: O(H) for Shared policy, O(log N + H) for Exclusive policy,
    where H is HeapCount and N is resources per shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) AcquireByAffinity(key acquire.AffinityIdentifier) (T, error)
    AcquireByAffinity retrieves a resource deterministically based on an
    affinity identifier. It bypasses the global AcquireStrategy, using an
    internal Consistent Hash Ring to route the request to a specific shard.
    This is ideal for sticky sessions.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. The Consistent Hash Ring lookup is
    allocation-free and read-optimized, and only the target Heap Shard is locked
    during the operation.

    Complexity: O(log V + log N) where V is the number of virtual nodes and N is
    resources per shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Add(res T) error
    Add inserts a single resource into the scheduler. It uses an internal Round
    Robin algorithm to assign the resource to a target Heap Shard. It returns
    ErrDuplicateResource if the resource key already exists.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. The Round Robin atomic counter ensures
    balanced distribution without locking, and insertion locks only the target
    shard.

    Complexity: O(log N) where N is the number of resources in the target shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) BatchAdd(resources []T) error
    BatchAdd atomically validates and inserts multiple resources. It operates
    in two phases: Phase 1 strictly validates all elements (nil checks,
    internal batch duplicates, and global registry duplicates) without modifying
    any state. Phase 2 safely distributes the valid batch across shards.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It maintains consistency by locking
    shards sequentially, avoiding global locks. Partial insertions never occur.

    Complexity: O(B * log N) where B is batch size and N is resources per shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Exclude(id ID) error
    Exclude manually moves an ACTIVE resource to the Inactive Store. This is
    typically used to temporarily remove a faulty resource from circulation
    (e.g., during a cooldown period).

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It locks the owning shard, removes the
    node, and places it into the locked Inactive Store.

    Complexity: O(log N) where N is the number of resources in the target shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Get(id ID) (T, error)
    Get retrieves a resource by its unique identifier without altering its
    state. It returns the resource value regardless of whether it is ACTIVE or
    INACTIVE.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe and RWMutex-protected. It uses the
    concurrent global Lookup Map.

    Complexity: O(1).

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Include(id ID) error
    Include restores a previously excluded resource back to its ACTIVE state.
    The resource is returned to its original native Heap Shard and becomes
    available for acquisition.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It atomically moves the node from the
    Inactive Store into the corresponding locked Heap Shard.

    Complexity: O(log N) where N is the number of resources in the target shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Len() int
    Len returns the total number of resources registered in the scheduler.
    This includes both ACTIVE resources and INACTIVE resources.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe and RWMutex-protected. It queries the
    concurrent global Lookup Map.

    Complexity: O(1).

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Release(id ID) error
    Release returns a previously exclusively acquired resource back to the
    scheduler. It restores the resource to its native Heap Shard and makes it
    ACTIVE again. It returns ErrNotExclusive if the scheduler is not using the
    Exclusive policy.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It performs an O(1) concurrent-safe
    lookup followed by a single-shard lock.

    Complexity: O(log N) where N is the number of resources in the target shard.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Remove(id ID) error
    Remove permanently deletes a resource from the scheduler. It works
    seamlessly whether the resource is ACTIVE in a Heap Shard or INACTIVE in the
    Inactive Store, removing all global lookup references.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It locates the node and cleanly locks
    either the target shard or the Inactive Store to perform the removal.

    Complexity: O(log N) for ACTIVE resources, O(1) for INACTIVE resources.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Shutdown()
    Shutdown permanently closes the scheduler and halts all background
    processing. It stops the event dispatcher goroutine to prevent leaks and
    marks the scheduler as closed, causing all subsequent operations to return
    ErrSchedulerClosed.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It uses atomic flags to ensure
    idempotent execution.

    Lifecycle: This method MUST be called when the scheduler is no longer
    needed.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Stats() stats.Stats
    Stats returns a point-in-time snapshot of the scheduler's internal metrics.
    It aggregates data across all Heap Shards and the Inactive Store to provide
    deep operational visibility.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It acquires short-lived locks on
    individual shards iteratively, never halting the entire scheduler or
    starving Acquire operations.

    Complexity: O(H) where H is the number of Heap Shards.

func (s *Scheduler[T, ID]) Update(res T) error
    Update replaces the value of an existing resource and recalculates its
    priority. If the resource is ACTIVE, it locks the owning shard and triggers
    a heap fix to restore the priority queue invariants. If INACTIVE, it safely
    updates the value in the Inactive Store.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It identifies the resource location via
    O(1) concurrent-safe lookup and strictly takes either the target shard lock
    or the Inactive Store lock.

    Complexity: O(log N) for ACTIVE resources, O(1) for INACTIVE resources.

