package acquire // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/acquire"


TYPES

type AcquireStrategy interface {
	// Select receives a read-only shard view and returns a zero-based Heap Shard index
	// for the scheduler to query.
	Select(view ShardView) int
}
    AcquireStrategy abstracts the target selection algorithm for Acquire
    operations.

    Behavior: The strategy decides *where* the scheduler begins its search for
    an available resource.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Implementations MUST be strictly thread-safe and
    non-blocking.

func NewRoundRobin() AcquireStrategy
    NewRoundRobin creates a strategy that cycles through shards sequentially.

    Behavior: It distributes traffic evenly irrespective of load.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It uses a single atomic increment for
    lock-free advancement.

type AdaptiveStrategy struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    AdaptiveStrategy probabilistically favors Heap Shards with fewer active
    resources.

    Behavior: It evaluates the load on all shards using the atomic ActiveCount
    view and weights selection heavily toward the least contended shards.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. It does not introduce any global locks.

func NewAdaptiveStrategy() *AdaptiveStrategy
    NewAdaptiveStrategy creates a strategy that dynamically balances load.

    Lifecycle: Provided to config.AcquireStrategy during initialization.

func (s *AdaptiveStrategy) Select(view ShardView) int
    Select evaluates current shard active counts and returns a candidate shard.

    Complexity: O(H) where H is the total number of shards.

func (s *AdaptiveStrategy) String() string
    String identifies the strategy.

    Complexity: O(1).

type AffinityIdentifier interface {
	// AppendAffinityBytes appends the identifier's raw byte representation to dst
	// and returns the updated slice. It must be deterministic.
	// The scheduler provides a small stack buffer. Implementations should append
	// to it when possible, but may allocate if their identifier exceeds the
	// provided capacity. The scheduler never retains the returned slice.
	AppendAffinityBytes(dst []byte) []byte
}
    AffinityIdentifier is implemented by application keys requesting Sticky
    Sessions.

    Behavior: Exposes bytes for internal hashing to deterministically route
    requests to consistent shards via the internal Consistent Hash Ring.

type ConsistentHashRing struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    ConsistentHashRing maps arbitrary uint64 hashes to stable Heap Shards.

    Behavior: Utilizes virtual nodes to ensure even distribution and minimizes
    migration if shard counts hypothetically change.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. The ring topology is immutable after
    creation.

func NewConsistentHashRing(shardCount int) *ConsistentHashRing
    NewConsistentHashRing constructs a hash ring tailored to the given shard
    count.

    Complexity: O(V log V) where V is virtual nodes (fixed ratio to shard
    count).

func (r *ConsistentHashRing) GetShard(hash uint64) int
    GetShard performs a binary search to find the closest virtual node on the
    ring.

    Complexity: O(log V) where V is the total number of virtual nodes.

type ShardView interface {
	// ShardCount returns the number of configured Heap Shards.
	ShardCount() int
	// ActiveCount returns the number of ACTIVE resources currently contained in the specified Heap Shard.
	ActiveCount(shard int) int
}
    ShardView abstracts read-only access to scheduler topology.

    Behavior: Exposes the number of shards and atomic active resource counts,
    allowing strategies to make load-aware decisions without mutating scheduler
    internals.

type WeightedStrategy struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    WeightedStrategy distributes traffic proportionally based on static
    capacities.

    Behavior: Higher weight shards receive more traffic. It utilizes an internal
    splitmix64 avalanche RNG per selection to maintain statistical distribution.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe. The internal state advances atomically.

func NewWeightedStrategy(weights []uint) *WeightedStrategy
    NewWeightedStrategy creates a capacity-aware acquire strategy.

    Behavior: Reverts to RoundRobin if weights are empty or uniform.

func (s *WeightedStrategy) Select(view ShardView) int
    Select performs an O(log W) binary search over the accumulated weight
    distribution.

    Complexity: O(log W) where W is the number of provided weights.

func (s *WeightedStrategy) String() string
    String identifies the strategy.

    Complexity: O(1).

