package events // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/events"


TYPES

type Event[ID comparable] struct {
	Type EventType
	ID   ID
}
    Event describes a single state transition for a specific resource.

    Behavior: It intentionally omits a timestamp to prevent time.Now() syscall
    overhead in the scheduler's hot path. It passes the resource ID instead of
    the full object to avoid concurrent mutation races.

type EventType int
    EventType represents a distinct lifecycle transition within the scheduler.

    Behavior: Identifies what operation triggered an event (e.g., EventAcquire,
    EventRelease).

const (
	EventAdd EventType = iota
	EventAcquire
	EventRelease
	EventExclude
	EventInclude
	EventRemove
	EventUpdate
)
func (t EventType) String() string
    String returns a human-readable representation of the EventType.

    Complexity: O(1).

type Observer[ID comparable] interface {
	OnEvent(e Event[ID])
}
    Observer provides a contract for external components to passively receive
    events.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Implementations MUST NOT block. The scheduler
    invokes OnEvent from a dedicated background goroutine. A blocking observer
    will cause the internal event channel to drop events silently to protect
    scheduler throughput.

