package cooldown // import "github.com/phero20/concurrent-resource-scheduler/extensions/cooldown"


TYPES

type LifecycleController[ID comparable] interface {
	Exclude(id ID) error
	Include(id ID) error
}
    LifecycleController abstracts the scheduler's manual inclusion/exclusion
    operations.

    Behavior: This interface allows the Cooldown Manager to manipulate the
    Inactive Store without introducing a circular package dependency on the
    scheduler core.

type Manager[ID comparable] struct {
	// Has unexported fields.
}
    Manager is an events.Observer that automatically places released resources
    into a temporary cooldown state.

    Important: Cooldown is implemented as an asynchronous Observer.
    Resources become excluded asynchronously after Release(). There exists a
    very small eventual-consistency window between Release() and Exclude().
    This is an intentional tradeoff to preserve the scheduler's non-blocking
    event architecture. Applications requiring strict synchronous cooldown
    enforcement should implement cooldown inside scheduler logic instead of
    using the observer extension.

    Behavior: When a resource is released, the Manager intercepts the event,
    calls Exclude(), and sets a timer to call Include() after the specified
    duration.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Thread-safe and non-blocking. It delegates delays to
    time.AfterFunc.

func NewManager[ID comparable](controller LifecycleController[ID], duration time.Duration) *Manager[ID]
    NewManager initializes a Cooldown Manager with the provided controller and
    duration.

    Lifecycle: The returned Manager should be registered in the config.Observers
    slice during scheduler initialization.

func (m *Manager[ID]) OnEvent(e events.Event[ID])
    OnEvent processes scheduler events asynchronously.

    Behavior: If the event is EventRelease, it triggers a cooldown for the
    resource.

    Concurrency Guarantees: Strictly non-blocking. It fires goroutines for timer
    callbacks.

